Guide to the City Club of New York Records 1890-1978 MS 116
New-York Historical Society
City Club of New York records
1892-1978
New-York Historical Society
City Club of New York
MS 116
23.67 Linear feet in 70 volumes, 11 record cartons, and 1 flat box
This collection documents the work of City Club of New York from 1892 to 1978. City Club of New York was a social and civic organization that worked towards legislative reform, city development and preservation, and welfare related issues including public health and education. Much of the collection is minutes and correspondence for the Club, Board of Trustees, and the club's committees, as well as materials related to the Club House up through 1943. These records include petitions, reports, bulletins, financials, membership materials, and proposed policy and legislative proposals of City Club and its various committees. The materials document the internal work of the club and its external publications, press releases, and dealings with various government and civic leaders.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Administrative History
The City Club of New York was founded in 1892 as a gentlemen's social and civic club in Manhattan with the purpose of "providing through the facilities of a social club, means of intercourse and co-operation among citizens, officials and organizations interested in the city's welfare." For 50 years they maintained a Club House for members at 55 West 44th Street that included a library, dining room and bar, office space and rooms rented to members and other organizations. At its peak around the 1920s, the club had over 1000 members.
City Club's civic work was for nonpartisan reform of New York government, both at the state and city level. Through the creation of over 70 committees and sub-committees, they lobbied for parks, playgrounds, improved housing conditions, hospitals and healthcare, education reform, and renovations of streets, transit, and the ports of New York. They also pushed for reform of various agencies including the New York Police Department, the courts, and the Parks Department. Their numerous publications, pamphlets, and circulating bulletins detail not just the work of the committees, but City Club's opinion on countless civic and legislative matters.
City Club lobbied in favor of the protection and preservation of historic buildings and parks throughout the city including the Old Assay building façade, Castle Clinton, Central Park, and Washington Square Park. Their position on various redesigns, rezoning, and renovations placed them continuously in contact with Parks Commissioner Robert Moses, most notably in opposition to his proposal to redesign Washington Square Park. While they became well known for opposing many of Moses's plans, they worked in favor of many others and honored Moses numerous times. They allied themselves with several other civic groups including Women's City Club of New York, the National Municipal League, and Citizens' Union.
In the 1940s City Club's purpose and plans shifted after the foreclosure of the Club House and subsequent move to the Hotel Russel in 1943. The social club with a civic purpose pushed forward a primarily civic agenda up until the 1950s when declining membership prompted a discussion of the dissolution of the Club. Dissolution was deemed not an option by younger members and in 1951 City Club underwent reorganization. The influx of younger members and increased membership to the Board and Committees solidified City Club's place as a civic organization.
In 1954 City Club gave up its offices at Hotel Russel and moved into the office of a member of the Board of Trustees. The move to an office space without a dining room or other social areas permanently solidified City Club's place as a solely civic organization. In 1959 City Club Comments, a newsletter edited by I. D. Robbins, began, and was circulated to both members and non-members. The Comments replaced the solely informative City Club Bulletin with political and social commentary written by and for readers of the newsletter. The organization remained a men's club until 1973 when the first female members joined.
City Club suspended its activities in 2003 due to funding, and in 2009 dissolved but retained their corporate charter. In 2013 it resumed its work under the guidance of Michael Gruen, the new president, with a renewed focus on urban development and preservation in New York City.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series.
Series I. Bound Minutes Books, 1892-1894,1904-1943
Series II. Records and Correspondence Files, 1890-1957
Subseries II.A. Trustee and Executive Committee Files, 1930-1953
Subseries II.B. General Correspondence, 1945-1952
Subseries II.C. Committees, 1937-1954
Subseries II.D. Events, 1941-1952
Subseries II.E. Club History, 1890-1951
Subseries II.F. Bulletins, 1938-1953
Subseries II.G. Miscellaneous, 1943-1957
Series III. Scrapbooks, 1911-1953
Series IV. Publications, 1892-1950,1959-1978
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Permanent deposit by City Club of New York, 1954. Later accruals in 1959 and approximately 1978.
Related Materials
At the New-York Historical Society:
New-York Historical also holds on the shelf many of the reports, periodicals, and constitutions of City Club, including a newsletter, The City Club Gadfly. These can be found by searching "City Club" in Bobcat.
At the New York Public Library:
City Club of New York records, 1896-2008 are located at the New York Public Library and include minutes, reports, and materials from 1960 onwards.
At Hunter College Libraries:
Women's City Club of New York, Inc. (Records of), 1955-2011 are located at Hunter College Libraries and include annual reports, minutes, committee reports, scrapbooks, and publications.
Scope and Contents
The City Club of New York records detail the Club's history and civic work from 1892 through to 1978. Most of the materials are from 1900 to 1957, and consist of minutes and materials from the club and its various committees including published and internal reports, legislation, correspondence, membership rosters, news clippings, and their bulletins. The materials consist of bound minute books and publications, files of correspondence, minutes, and other records, booklets, pamphlets, newsletters, ephemera, and four scrapbooks.
Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; Education -- 20th century; Public health -- New York (State) -- New York.; Housing -- New York (State) -- New York.; City planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Public policy.; Local transit.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic preservation.; Local government -- New York (State) -- New York; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Printed ephemera.; Memorandums.; Correspondence.; Scrapbooks.; Reports.; Annual reports.; Financial statements.; Membership lists.; Press releases.; Clippings (information artifacts); Bills (legislative records); Childs, Richard S. (Richard Spencer), 1882-1978; City Club of New York -- Archives; Weis, Walter M.; Robbins, I. D., 1913-1996; Women's City Club of New York; Moses, Robert, 1888-1981
- Series I. Bound Minutes Books, 1892-1894, 1904-1943; 12 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series are the bound volumes of minutes of City Club's Board of Trustees, Executive Committee, annual meetings, and miscellaneous committees up to 1940. Minutes from after 1940 were not bound and are located within the Records and Correspondence Files series. The volumes include minutes, correspondence, financials, reports of the committees, and other materials.
  The Board of Trustee minutes contain financials, committee reports, correspondence and other materials. Executive Committee minutes also include various committee updates, resignations, elections, membership updates and financials of the Club. There are volumes for Minutes of the Club which contain updates, election results, reports, membership, and notices of meetings. One volume of Minutes of the Club is combined with membership minutes for that year. Membership minutes include updates on elections, resignations, transfers, dropped members, reinstatements, member rosters, and miscellaneous related materials. There is one volume of City Affairs minutes, and five volumes of Legislation Committee minutes which contain lists of legislation the committee was monitoring and their position on it: favor, opposed, or no action.
  The volumes of Miscellaneous Committee Minutes contain the minutes of various committees, special committees and sub-committees. There are variations in how committee names are presented. The topics of committees include city affairs, legislation, city planning and development, finance, public health, nominations, courts, parks, education, housing, transit and transportation, taxation, port development, employment, the re-chartering of New York, and the House Committee. Other various temporary special committees, sub-committees, and committees are noted at the volume level.
  Arrangement
  The volumes are arranged in chronological order within committee groupings: Board of Trustees, Executive, Membership, Committees. Several binders were taken apart due to damage and placed into folders with the front cover. All materials placed into folders are according to original order within the binder.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1904 (Offsite-box CC-1, Volume 1.a)
    Includes letter regarding dual membership at Seawanhaka Corinthian Yacht Club, letter regarding Croton Aquaduct and water supply, and memorandums.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1905 (Offsite-box CC-1, Volume 1.b)
    Includes minutes and materials regarding the New York and New Jersey tunnel franchise, membership dues by borough, the preservation of trees in Central Park and newsclippings, records of City Club pamphlets and papers destroyed by the assistant secretary, Library Committee reports, and materials on pool rooms and illegal gambling.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1906 (Offsite-box CC-1, Volume 2)
    Includes minutes, finances, materials regarding Rapid Transit, 11 page resignation of the Secretary due to mismanagement of club and civic actions, committee reports, voting suggestions for legislation, membership and dues list, report of the Special Committee on the financial condition of the Club, and inventory of club house rooms.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1907 (Offsite-box CC-1, Volume 3)
    Includes resignations and materials regarding proposed elevated loop, finances, membership materials, and proposed amendments to Club constitution.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1908 (Offsite-box CC-1, Volume 4)
    Includes materials regarding Atlantic Telephone Company's possible monopology (monopoly), finances, Rapid Transit Railroads report, amended by-laws and house rules, snow removal reports, and membership reports.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1909 (Offsite-box CC-2, Volume 5)
    Includes finances, memnbership materials, reports to the Board regarding East River bridges, report regarding plans to build a stadium in Morningside Park, report by Special Committee on telephone practices, correspondence, and news clipping regarding finances.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1910 (Offsite-box CC-2, Volume 6)
    Includes notes regarding Women's Suffrage luncheon, City Club Realty Company, real estate, finances, public health, and correspondence.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1911 (Offsite-box CC-2, Volume 7)
    Includes committee rosters, transit memorandums and report on future subway platforms for longer trains, correspondence, letter regarding women dining in private rooms to not interfere with male members, report on committee on Women's Auxiliary, report regarding ballot marks and validity, taxicab ordinances, letter protesting allowing women to wear hats at luncheons, letter requesting the removal of coroners as undertakers and report, and proposed amendments to code of criminal procedure.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees Jan-June, 1912 (Offsite-box CC-2, Volume 8)
    Includes correspondence regarding invitations, report on number of passengers needed to meet expenses for interborough subway, and report suggesting a hospital for contagious diseases be built in the Bronx.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees July-Dec., 1912 (Offsite-box CC-2, Volume 9)
    Includes report on Eleventh Avenue subway, pamphlet arguing for a contagious disease hospital in the Bronx, correspondence and map of proposed Third Avenue subway entrance, collection of reports of Courts Committee with proposed amendments, amendments to Club constitution including Club purpose.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1913 (Offsite-box CC-3, Volume 10)
    Includes report on Interborough Transit Company contract, correspondence regarding closing of Savoy and Dewey theatres by Fire Commissioner, correspondence to Fire Commissioner regarding the Carnegie Lyceum's lack of exits and map of theatre, correspondence regarding incorporation and leasing of Century Opera House for popular opera, memorandum for preservation of St. John's Chapel, correspondence regarding removal of elevated railway and hand drawn maps.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1914 (Offsite-box CC-3, Volume 11)
    Includes draft of charges for removal of John Voohris for inefficiency, pamphlet proposing construction of a new East River from Flushing to Jamaica Bay and filling in of the East River, and correspondence regarding film censorship of a film including a prostitute as heroine.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1915 (Offsite-box CC-3, Volume 12)
    Includes correspondence about membership, Executive Committee minutes, letter from Court House Board that a new court house location has been acquired after 27 years of discussion, correspondence and map of proposed Fulton Street elevated railway, and denied request for women's suffrage group to come and speak before election day.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1916 (Offsite-box CC-3, Volume 13)
    Includes transcript of meeting to hear charges against member Benjamin Marsh for his actions and motion to investigate the Board of Trustees, response letters from Marsh, correspondence regarding purchase of new Clubhouse, and letter regarding "daylight savings movement."
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1917 (Offsite-box CC-4, Volume 14)
    Includes charges against Edward Swann District Attorney, pamphlet on proposed daylight saving time, reports on creation of a State Farm Colony for Vagrants, Memorandum on New York Central track relocation, and reports on war ambulance fund.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1918 (Offsite-box CC-4, Volume 15)
    Includes minutes allowing organizations to utilize City Club space for meetings that include women members, formation of a committee to discuss democratic elections and women's work in the club, discussion of Prohibition and the Club's stance, amendments to by-laws regarding service men and "allied German sympathizers," correspondence regarding members being potential German sympathizers, privileges of women at City Club, and a copy of City Club Reconstruction Program.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1919 (Offsite-box CC-4, Volume 16)
    Includes petitions to limit women's privileges at the club, correspondence regarding tax exemption, and report on proposed cross Jersey canal.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1920-1921 (Offsite-box CC-4, Volume 17)
    Includes report "Justice and the Poor" and news clipping, drawing of proposed buildings for west side for garment workers, December Bulletin, release on Governor's traction bill on transportation, notice of dissolution of Century Opera Company, and notice on Armistice Day dinner.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1922-1924 (Offsite-box CC-5, Volume 18)
    Includes statement from Citizens Committee of America on the state of hospitals for wounded men and establishment of a hospital for tuberculosis treatment, correspondence regarding New Netherland Bank account, release on proposed improvements around Grand Central Station, education program developed by City Club, memorandum on transit bill, City Club Bulletins, and minutes regarding the need for more parks and facilities for New York's growing African American population.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1925-1927 (Offsite-box CC-5, Volume 19)
    Includes minutes regarding transit legislation, removal of religious curriculum from public schools, letter regarding how to make the club more economical in its functions, plans to purchase the remaining City Club Realty stock, proposed New York state constitutional amendment to Article VIII, suggestions to the State Reorganization Commission, materials regarding proposed legislation, and three-page program regarding changes for schools, subways, and tenements.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1928-1930 (Offsite-box CC-5, Volume 20)
    Includes minutes on proposition for the creation of a city museum, release supporting the West Side improvement plan, civic fund and membership report, correspondence regarding release about Consolidated Gas Company's history and its financials, 23 page memorandum on the Consolidated Gas Company controversy, and minutes on creation of a committee to report on Communists meetings.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1931-1932 (Offsite-box CC-5, Volume 21)
    Includes copy of act to create a Bureau of Municipal Affairs, estimates for repair of the clubhouse, minutes about Osborn plan to create avenue through Central Park, copy of resolutions of directors of City Club Realty Company, City Club Bulletins, Report on Judicial Councils and foldout, report on mortgage foreclosure receiverships, reform of supplementary proceedings, and simplification of foreclosure suits.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1933-1934 (Offsite-box CC-6, Volume 22)
    Includes minutes regarding proposed bills on minimum wage, letter to Board of Estimate and Apportionment regarding the City's financial problems, correspondence to New York Grand Jury regarding racketeering, City Club Veteran Reference Amendment, memorandum on the conference on transit unification, and colonization plan of removal from New York due to unemployment.
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees (6 folders), 1935-1940 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-6)
    Includes memorandum on city rezoning, Trustee resignation letters, statement on proposed recreation planning for N.Y. World's Fair 1939, report on mortgage moratorium, report on club affairs regarding debt and the club's future, memorandum on scope of program for City Club's future, materials on Washington Square Park renovations, materials on foreclosure of the City Club building, and report on proposed "V Plan."
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1940-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
    Includes proposed civic program (1940-1941), Luncheon Menu (1942), materials regarding absence of students for religious education in public schools, comment on the proposed rapid transit fare increase (1942), note of admission of African Americans to City Club (March 30, 1942), and minutes of Special Committee on membership regarding continuance of City Club.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1904-1907 (Offsite-box CC-6, Volume 23)
    Includes minutes discussing potential elevated road extensions, a police bill, adjustment of lease from City Club Realty Company, notes on Board of Education hearing on eye glasses for school children, and Atlantic Telephone Franchise materials.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1908-1910 (Offsite-box CC-6, Volume 24)
    Includes discussion of Ahearn investigation and cost to City Club, transit bills, copy of section 1829 of the Penal Law, and letters regarding John Fox's payment for services to the club.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1911-1912 (Offsite-box CC-6, Volume 25)
    Includes pamphlet "The So-called Gaynor Charter", copy of Section 109 of the Building Code, letter regarding proposed changes to the city charter, card advertising City Club charter conferences (1911), resolution on fire protection and pledges of support, correspondence regarding committee updates and reports, letter to members on subway expansion, and copy of insurance policy for City Club property.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1913-1915 (Offsite-box CC-7, Volume 26)
    Includes letter regarding plans for waterfront property improvements and report, announcement of Committee on Popular Opera and other materials, correspondence with National Board of Censorship, correspondence regarding Kenyon Law and Herrick Bill to act against houses of prostitution as public nuisances, contribution letter (1914), materials regarding proposals to save the facade of the Old Assay Building, memorandum on Horton-Stoddard Bill by Citizen's Union, resolutions on quarantine control from American Board of Medicine, 15 page letter response to New York Edison Company's electricity report, and State Constitutional changes pamphlet from Citizen's Union.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1916-1917 (Offsite-box CC-7, Volume 27)
    Includes reorganization of Committee work, letter and hand drawn map of potential new club house site, and letter from Mayor and draft to endorse breaking off of diplomatic relations with Germany.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box CC-7, Volume 28)
    Includes war time housing report, statement from City Club on Terminal Improvement Commission, and draft of report on Vault Rentals.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1920-1927 (Offsite-box CC-7, Volume 29)
    Includes hearing on the proposed St. Lawrence ship canal, report of Committee on Automobile Accidents, letter regarding Coney Island bathhouse, dissolution notice of Century Opera Company, letter regarding proposed subway through Central Park, and report on New York State government reorganization.
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1934-1940 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
    Includes release on Robert Moses protest and rumors, and plans for club finances.
  - Minutes of the Club, 1904-1907 (Offsite-box CC-8, Volume 30)
    Includes transcript of special meeting on City Club constitutional changes and the Elsberg Rapid Transit Bill (1905), transcript of annual meeting 1906 including discussion of rapid transit bills, ballot reform, franchises, bridge problems, and parks, and proposed amendments to the constitution (1907).
  - Minutes of the Club, 1908-1912 (Offsite-box CC-8, Volume 31)
    Includes report on election laws (1908), bills considered by Board of Trustees, report of committee on fire protection, annual reports of Board of Trustees, and copy of address by Frederic Howe "The Police, Excise and Gambling Evil."
  - Minutes of the Club & Membership Committee, 1913-1916 (Offsite-box CC-8, Volume 32)
    Combined volume of minutes of the club and minutes of the membership committee. Includes Annual reports.
  - Minutes of the Club, 1917-1935 (Offsite-box CC-8, Volume 33)
    Includes memorandum on relocation of New York Central Railway tracks, letter to members on club updates (1918), annual reports, and copies of Club Bulletins.
  - Minutes of the Membership Committee, 1904-1907 (Offsite-box CC-9, Volume 34)
    Includes report on changes in membership rules.
  - Minutes of the Membership Committee, 1908-1912 (Offsite-box CC-9, Volume 35)
    Includes letter protesting City Club becoming a haven for Hebrew members who are barred from other clubs, news clipping regarding the suicide of member Siegfried Hayman at City Club, and annotated list of Life Members.
  - Minutes of the Membership Committee, 1917-1919 (Offsite-box CC-9, Volume 36)
  - Minutes of the Membership Committee, 1920-1923 (Offsite-box CC-9, Volume 37)
  - Minutes of the Membership Committee, 1924-1928 (Offsite-box CC-10, Volume 38)